Three artists have brought a lawsuit against Stability AI, DeviantArt, and Midjourney, alleging that the text-to-image AI tools have infringed the rights of thousands of artists.
三位艺术家对Stability AI、DeviantArt和Midjourney提起了诉讼，指控这些文生图AI工具侵犯了数千名艺术家的权利。
The lawsuit claims that the Stable Diffusion tool used by Stability AI, DeviantArt, and Midjourney was trained on billions of copyrighted images downloaded from the internet and used by the companies “without compensation or consent from the artists”.
诉讼称，Stability AI、DeviantArt和Midjourney所使用的Stable Diffusion工具，是用从互联网上下载的数十亿张受版权保护的图像训练的，而这几家公司使用这些图像时，“既没有给予艺术家补偿，也没有征得他们的同意”。
The artists are represented by The Joseph Saveri Law Firm and Matthew Butterick.
这三位艺术家由约瑟夫·萨韦里律师事务所和马修·巴特里克代理。
“If Stable Diffusion and similar products are allowed to continue to operate as they do now, the foreseeable result is they will replace the very artists whose stolen works power these AI products with whom they are competing,” the law firm wrote in a press release.
该律师事务所在一份新闻稿中写道：“如果允许Stable Diffusion及类似产品继续像现在这样运作，可以预见的结果是，它们将取代的恰恰是这样一些艺术家：这些AI产品靠他们被盗用的作品驱动，又正在与他们竞争。”
“AI image products are not just an infringement of artists’ rights; they will eliminate ‘artist’ as a viable career path.
“AI图像产品不只是侵犯艺术家的权利，还会让‘艺术家’不再是一条可行的职业道路。
In addition to obtaining compensation for the wrongful conduct, this lawsuit seeks to prevent that outcome and ensure these products follow the same rules as any other new technology that involves the use of massive amounts of intellectual property.
这起诉讼除了要就这种不法行为获得赔偿，还力求防止出现这一结果，并确保这些产品与其他任何涉及使用海量知识产权的新技术遵守同样的规则。
If streaming music can be accomplished within the law, so can AI products.”
如果流媒体音乐能够在法律允许的范围内实现，那么AI产品也同样可以。”
Since text-to-image generators have increased in popularity in the past year, many artists have been vocalizing their opposition to AI art after seeing their own distorted signatures appear in AI art and finding out that their work was used to train the tools without their permission.
随着文生图生成器在过去一年里越来越受欢迎，许多艺术家看到自己的签名以扭曲的形式出现在AI艺术作品中，又发现自己的作品未经许可就被用来训练这些工具，此后便一直公开表示反对AI艺术。
Not only are many artists furious at the possible copyright violations of AI art, but they have also been frustrated by how AI tools are able to sidestep the labor and art processes they are required to go through.
许多艺术家不仅对AI艺术可能存在的侵犯版权行为极为愤怒，而且一直对AI工具能够绕开他们必须经历的劳动和艺术创作过程感到沮丧。
As a result, many artists have been trying to ban AI art from art-sharing platforms.
因此，许多艺术家一直试图禁止AI艺术作品进入艺术分享平台。
As AI innovation continues at a rapid speed, it seems that artists and lawmakers are trying to put a brake on further developments before it’s too late.
随着AI创新持续快速推进，艺术家和立法者似乎正试图趁为时未晚，给进一步的发展踩刹车。
Many tech enthusiasts are still rallying around the promise of AI tools to create detailed images cheaply and quickly—anonymous tech supporters have already published a response to Butterick and Joseph Saveri’s lawsuit on a website, using the “fair use” clause as the basis for why copyrighted images could be used by the tool.
许多科技爱好者仍在力挺AI工具，看好它们以低廉的成本快速生成精细图像的前景——一些匿名的科技支持者已在一个网站上就巴特里克和约瑟夫·萨韦里代理的这起诉讼发表了回应，以“合理使用”条款为依据，说明该工具为何可以使用受版权保护的图像。
Fair use, a legal doctrine that allows for a limited usage of copyrighted materials without permission from the original creators for purposes such as teaching and news sharing, is what a lot of generative model creators claim that their training data is covered by.
合理使用是一项法律原则，允许出于教学、新闻分享等目的，在未经原创作者许可的情况下有限度地使用受版权保护的材料；许多生成式模型的开发者声称，他们的训练数据受到的正是这一原则的保护。
However, since fair use applies differently to each case, it’s hard to make a blanket statement that all works in a dataset are covered.
然而，由于合理使用的适用情况因案而异，很难笼统地断言一个数据集中的所有作品都受其保护。